So we resume on the bottom of מ"ב, Mem Bet,
well not the bottom I wish, the first of the medium sized
lines that the two dots בית שמאי אומרים מכבדין. Beit Shammai omrim
mechabdin. So do you first clear off the crumbs and then do
the נטילת ידים, Netilat yadayim, here the מים אחרונים, Mayim acharonim, or
do you reverse it? בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you first clear
off the crumbs. תנו רבנן בית שמאי אומרים מכבדין את הבית ואחר
כך נוטלין לידים, Tanu rabanan Beit Shammai omrim mechabdin et habayit ve’achar
kach notlin layadayim, first clear off the crumbs and then you do
the מים אחרונים. Mayim acharonim. ובית הלל אומרים נוטלין לידים ואחר כך
מכבדין את הבית, U’Beit Hillel omrim notlin layadayim ve’achar kach mechabdin et
habayit, if you first do מים אחרונים, Mayim acharonim, נמצא אתה מפסיד
את האוכלין, Nimtza ata mafsid et ha’ochlin, the water will spill on
the bread crumbs and there's I guess not so tiny crumbs you'll
want to eat them later and it'll get them, it'll ruin them.
אבל נטילת ידים לבית שמאי תחילה לא סבירא להו, Aval netilat yadayim
le’Beit Shammai techila lo sevira lehu, some take out that line because
it's redundant it doesn't add anything. Anyway, בית שמאי Beit Shammai does
not insist that you first wash hands, they say whatever, first go
ahead and clear off the crumbs. Maybe the concern is like should
the washing of hands come immediately when you're done eating, especially because
it's also to get rid of the dirt and the smell and
the מלח סדומית, Melach Sedomit, and you want to get that stuff
off right away? But they're more concerned about first that you get
scrape the crumbs away so you don't ruin them with the
water. מאי טעמא? Mai ta’ama? משום פירורין, Mishum peirurin, because it's only
tiny little crumbs and they're not concerned about that. ובית הלל אומרים
אם שמש תלמיד חכם הוא, U’Beit Hillel omrim im shamash talmid chacham
hu, נוטל את הפירורין שיש בהן כזית. Notel et hapeirurin she’yesh bahen
kezayit. Look, if the attendant is a תלמיד חכם, Talmid chacham, it's
interesting that you have to be a תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham for
this, then he'll know to take away the crumbs, the chunks of
bread that have a כזית, Kezayit, and those are ones that you
would want to eat later. He'll remove them beforehand anyway. ומניח את
הפירורין שאין בהן כזית. U’maniach et hapeirurin she’ein bahen kezayit. So we're
just talking about the only crumbs that would be left would be
little crumbs that don't have a כזית Kezayit and who cares if
you ruin those? Nobody's interested in eating them
anyway. מסייע ליה לרבי יוחנן, Mesayei leih le’Rabbi Yochanan, דאמר רבי יוחנן
פירורין שאין בהן כזית מותר לאבדן ביד, De’amar Rabbi Yochanan peirurin she’ein
bahen kezayit mutar le’abdan beyad, that although we had a whole discussion
a day or two ago about בזוי אוכלין, Bizui ochlin, but if
you have crumbs less than a כזית Kezayit that it's really not
even any substantial amount, you can even destroy them directly because nobody's
planning on eating them. Okay, so that would be what בית הלל
Beit Hillel
says. במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamifligi? So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamifligi? What is at the root of their debate?
בית הלל סברי אסור להשתמש בשמש עם הארץ. Beit Hillel savri assur
lehishtamesh beshamash am ha’aretz. This is quite fascinating given generally our normal
assumptions of בית הלל Beit Hillel being more sort of loving or
inclusive or whatever. בית הלל Beit Hillel still says you can't use
an attendant that's an עם הארץ. Am ha’aretz. So he's not concerned
about there being big chunks left over. ובית שמאי סברי מותר להשתמש
בשמש עם הארץ. U’Beit Shammai savri mutar lehishtamesh beshamash am ha’aretz. You
are allowed to, and therefore we are concerned that even at the
end of the meal there'll still be big chunks and you want
to first clear them away before נטילת ידים. Netilat yadayim. Now because
it is a little bit ironic how we would have thought it
came out, so here's the one case where אמר רבי יוסי ברבי
חנינא אמר רב הונא בכל פירקא הלכה כבית הלל. Amar Rabbi Yosi
berabi Chanina amar Rav Huna bechol pirka halacha ke’Beit Hillel. The whole
פירקא Pirka we rule like בית הלל, Beit Hillel, again it's a
little surprise you have to say that, but the point is בר
מהא, Bar meiha, except for this case about the crumbs and whether
you can use an attendant who's an עם הארץ. Am ha’aretz. ההלכה
כבית שמאי, Hahalacha ke’Beit Shammai, because we rule like בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. So in the end here בית שמאי Beit Shammai who sets
a tradition that we would normally think would be a בית הלל
Beit Hillel one, he wins out. רבי אושעיא מתני איפכא. Rabbi Oshaya
matni ipcha. רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya solves it another way, he reverses
the positions of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
ובהא נמי הלכה כבית הלל, U’beha nami halacha ke’Beit Hillel, and we
also rule like בית הלל Beit Hillel because he says בית הלל
Beit Hillel is the one that says you can use an attendant
who's not a תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham and therefore you have to
first clear off the crumbs before נטילת ידים. Netilat yadayim. Okay. Now
בית שמאי אומרים נר ומזון, Beit Shammai omrim ner u’mazon, now became
the whole question about if you have ברכת המזון Birkat hamazon and
הבדלה, Havdalah, you did הבדלה Havdalah at the end together with the
בענטשן Bensching on the כוס Kos that you did let's say for
סעודה שלישית. Seuda Shlishit. So where does the ברכת המזון Birkat hamazon
come in? It's quite fascinating in the משנה Mishna that it has
it right there sort of embedded in the middle of הבדלה. Havdalah.
And the only question was exactly where. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, רב הונא בר יהודה איקלע לבי רבא. Rav Huna bar
Yehuda ikla le’vei Rava. רב הונא בר יהודה Rav Huna bar Yehuda
came to the house of רבא. Rava. חזייה לרבא דבריך אבשמים ברישא.
Chazyei le’Rava de’varich abesamim reisha. So he first did בשמים, Besamim, which
is what we do, we do יין Yayin and then בשמים, Besamim,
but it's against the משנה Mishna that has both שמאי Shammai and
הלל Hillel saying, בית שמאי ובית הלל Beit Shammai ve’Beit Hillel saying
first you do נר. Ner. אמר ליה מכדי, Amar leih michdi, says
wait a minute, בית שמאי ובית הלל במאור לא פליגי. Beit Shammai
ve’Beit Hillel be’maor lo peligi. They're not debating whether the מאור Maor
comes first, that the נר Ner comes first. דתניא, Detanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, Braita, בית שמאי אומרים נר ומזון בשמים והבדלה, Beit
Shammai omrim ner u’mazon besamim ve’havdalah, ובית הלל אומרים נר ובשמים ומזון
והבדלה. u’Beit Hillel omrim ner u’vesamim u’mazon ve’havdalah. Everybody says first comes
נר, Ner, the only question is does the ברכת המזון Birkat hamazon
come before or after בשמים? Besamim?
So what are you doing doing בשמים Besamim first? עני רבא בתריה,
Ani Rava batreih, so רבא Rava responded, זו דברי רבי מאיר. Zu
divrei Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. אבל רבי יהודה
אומר לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על המזון. Aval Rabbi Yehuda
omer lo nechelku Beit Shammai ve’Beit Hillel al hamazon. He
says no, they didn't argue about ברכת המזון. Birkat hamazon. We quoted
this on the עמוד א'. Amud Aleph. They never argued about ברכת
המזון. Birkat hamazon. Everybody agrees that even if you're putting it all
together שבתחילה she’betchila that comes first, ועל הבדלה שהיא בסוף, ve’al havdalah
she’hi besof, and הבדלה Havdalah comes at the end, which makes a
lot of sense, first wrap up ברכת המזון Birkat hamazon and then
do הבדלה. Havdalah. Maybe it's not clear what the other understanding was,
maybe the question was how much do you want to juxtapose the
ברכת המזון Birkat hamazon to the בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagefen.
Since you want the כוס Kos to be both on the הבדלה
Havdalah and on the ברכת המזון, Birkat hamazon, maybe that's an issue
but anyway about like. moving the ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon earlier or
later. Still not exactly clear. Anyway, he says they didn't debate: ברכת
המזון Birchas Hamazon first, that's the first thing you're doing, הבדלה Havdalah
at the end, and then what did they debate? על המאור ועל
הבשמים, al ha-ma'or ve-al ha-besamim, the order of the מאור ma'or and
the בשמים. besamim. בית שמאי אומרים על המאור ואחר כך על הבשמים,
Beis Shammai omrim al ha-ma'or ve-achar kach al ha-besamim, first מאור ma'or
and then בשמים. besamim. בית הלל אומרים בשמים ואחר כך המאור, Beis
Hillel omrim besamim ve-achar kach ha-ma'or, so בשמים besamim and then light.
ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כבית הלל אליבא דרבי יהודה. ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan
halacha ke-Veis Hillel aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda. After he says בית הלל Beis
Hillel according to רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's approach, which means that we
do בשמים besamim first and then מאור. ma'or. And if you mix,
if you mess it up, it's okay, but that's the order that
we do. And in the case where you're combining it with ברכת
המזון, Birchas Hamazon, we would also do ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon at
the beginning. Not again, no discussion what this debate was about. I
mean, all the טומאה וטהרה Tumah ve-Taharah stuff they had to get
to the core of the debate. This we actually think might be
a little bit interesting from our perspective. No discussion about what that's
about about the מאור ma'or and the בשמים. besamim. Generally, the explanation
is that the מאור ma'or about the purpose that they serve and
we'll see is that the מאור ma'or is, well, both it's an
aspect of you weren't allowed to make fire on שבת, Shabbos, so
it's to signify the end of שבת Shabbos that way. That's why
we also do it on מוצאי יום כיפור. Motzaei Yom Kippur. But
there's another special aspect about that on מוצאי שבת, Motzaei Shabbos, which
is not just about lights in the world but about fire as
the first creative activity of humans, that the understanding of the מדרש
Midrash is that after שבת Shabbos the first thing אדם הראשון Adam
HaRishon did is he made fire. He rubbed two sticks together and
made fire or banged two rocks together and clearly, you know, that's
like the founding of civilization was the making and the taming of
fire. So to remember that. The בשמים besamim is really like to
restore, you know, a sense of we're sort of dispirited that שבת
Shabbos has left, we lost נשמה יתירה, neshama yesira, to revive us
a little bit. So in terms of those two, it's interesting, like
is it logical which one comes first? Why exactly we do it?
No discussion. Maybe בית הלל Beis Hillel just feels you need to
sort of, you know, be in a positive mood before you get
on, you know, you need to revive the person first. But again,
you know, and maybe but obviously it seems that the מאור ma'or
has a greater sort of religious message and that could be why
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says do it first. But again, maybe again
this is the normal בית הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai
that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says do מאור ma'or first, but maybe
בית הלל Beis Hillel is concerned more about the fact how you're
feeling and we'll address that first and then we'll get on to
the religious message. Anyway, that's just my interpretation, no discussion in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
Now, yes. Or could it be, I mean, the difference between מאור
ma'or and בשמים besamim is that מאור ma'or is a standard once-a-week
thing and בשמים besamim could be more.
Oh. So it's like the תדיר tadir discussion. Oh, that's interesting because
that has a parallel to the תדיר tadir discussion about the יין
yayin and the יום. yom. The same way בית הלל Beis Hillel
says יין yayin first, תדיר. tadir. בשמים besamim first, maybe it's תדיר.
tadir. That's a nice point. Okay. That's very nice. Still have to
explain בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, but that's nice for בית הלל. Beis
Hillel. Okay. Now the question is what's the text. So בית שמאי
אומרים שברא מאור האש Beis Shammai omrim she-bara ma'or ha-esh
and בית הלל אומרים בורא
מאורי האש. Beis Hillel omrim borei me'orei ha-esh. אמר רבא בברא כולי
עלמא לא פליגי דברא משמע. Amar Rava be-bara kuli alma lo peligi
de-bara mashma. Everybody agrees ברא bara means ברא. bara. Everybody agrees ברא
bara means in the past, God created. כי פליגי, ki peligi, what's
the debate? So in theory בית הלל Beis Hillel could have said
ברא. bara. What's the debate? בבורא, be-borei, the word בורא. borei. בית
שמאי סברי בורא דעתיד למברא, Beis Shammai savri borei de-asid lismibra, that
means you will in the future or maybe you are now and
you will in the future, but it does not suggest you have
in the past. ובית הלל סברי בורא נמי דברא משמע. u-Veis Hillel
savri borei nami de-bara mashma. They also includes בורא borei as ongoing
and it includes also in the past. מתיב רב יוסף, Masiv Rav
Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said how could they debate about
this? יוצר אור ובורא חושך, yotzer or u-vorei choshech, יוצר הרים ובורא
רוח, yotzer harim u-vorei ruach, בורא שמים ונוטיהם. borei shamayim ve-noteihem. So
here it's in the present בורא, borei, but it clearly means not
only in the present, but it means God has always done this
and has done this in the
past, the creator of. You know, also it could be a question
is it a verb or is it an adjective? Right? Is it
God... there's actually some grammarians discuss that, whether Hebrew really has a
present tense or whether you know the whole idea of
שומר שומרת, shomer shomeret, maybe that's just descriptive of the person, right,
not of sort of a present active verb. Anyway, so בורא, borei,
God is the creator of, right, if it's not a verb anyway
it's a descriptive, if it's an adjective then all the more so
that it includes the past. Anyway you have it clearly in all
these verses, so nobody would debate that that would work. אלא אמר
רב יוסף בברא ובורא כולי עלמא לא פליגי דברא משמע. ela amar
Rav Yosef be-bara u-vorei kuli alma lo peligi de-bara mashma. Everybody agrees
בורא borei can also mean the past. כי פליגי במאור ומאורי. ki
peligi be-ma'or u-me'orei. The key is the debate of מאור ma'or and
מאורי. me'orei. דבית שמאי סברי חדא נהורא איכא בנורא, de-Beis Shammai savri
chada nehora ika be-nura, that fundamentally there's one light in the flame
and therefore it's מאור, ma'or, the single. ובית הלל סברי טובא נהורא
איכא בנורא. u-Veis Hillel savri tuva nehora ika be-nura. There are many
different flames, you know, different colors and different flames within a fire.
תניא נמי הכי אמרו להם בית הלל לבית שמאי, tanya nami hachi
amru lahem Beis Hillel le-Beis Shammai, בית הלל Beis Hillel said to
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, הרבה מאורות יש באור, harbe me'oros yesh ba-or,
there are many flames and therefore you say מאורי. me'orei. Now there's
a famous גר"א Gra that he says, I don't know how famous
it is, anyway the גר"א Gra says, says what do you mean
that the גמרא Gemara ignores the בורא borei and the ברא? bara?
That's also part of the debate. They say that they differ. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says ברא, bara, בית הלל Beis Hillel says בורא.
borei. Also what is בית שמאי Beis Shammai saying that there's only
one like color of the flame, what's that about? So he says
that's exactly the debate part are interrelated, that he says like the
idea what he calls יסוד האש, yesod ha-esh, you know, maybe the
first creation of
fire, the whatever
this... The
Platonic fire is a singular. The real fire in this world is
multiple. So בית שמאי's Beis Shammai focusing on the past, God created
fire sort of as the abstract, the Platonic fire. That's ברא bara
in the past and it's מאור ma'or in the singular. Whereas בית
הלל Beis Hillel says no, we talk also about what how that
it's right now in our world as well. So it's בורא, borei,
it's ongoing, and it's מאורי me'orei because the way it is in
our world is multiple.
And that you could tie into normal ways to understand בית הלל
Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, that בית שמאי Beis Shammai
is very sort of idealistic about sort of how things are in
their ideal sortם שמים shamayim way, and בית הלל Beis Hillel is
much more rooted in the real world. So it doesn't really matter
about what the יסוד האש yesod ha'esh is. So that's a nice
explanation that the Vilna גאון Gaon has. You wouldn't have the idea
of the multiple flames. But anyway, that's not mentioned here. Now, אין
מברכין, ein mevarchin, you do not use light or בשמים besamim from
a non-Jew. So בשלמא bishlama נר ner משום דלא שבת. mishum delo
shavat. I understand light because it did not rest. The idea was
that maybe it was lit on שבת Shabbos and therefore, although non-Jews
aren't commanded, but there's a sense that that was the product of
a violation of שבת. Shabbos. And the whole idea of the light
is that it is showing you couldn't light before now.
אבל בשמים מאי טעמא לא? aval besamim mai ta'ama lo? Why not
use בשמים besamim of non-Jews? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב הכא במסבת
עובדי כוכבים עסקינן. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav hacha bemesibat ovdei kochavim
askinan.
We're talking about fragrances that were used at a sort of at
a meal, at a feast of non-Jews. דמסתמא מסבת עובדי כוכבים לעבודה
זרה היא demistama mesibat ovdei kochavim l'avoda zara hi
because we assume that if they're having a feast, that they're doing
it also in honor of their gods, and therefore these בשמים besamim
are associated with עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute. הא מדקתני סיפא, ha midekatni seifa, the end of the
משנה mishnah says, אין מברכין לא על הנר ולא על הבשמים של
עבודה זרה, ein mevarchin lo al haner velo al habesamim shel avoda
zara, that you don't make it on when they're associated with עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. מכלל דרישא, michlal dereisha, at the beginning when it's
talking about just owned by
non-Jews, מכלל דלאו עבודה זרה עסקינן, michlal delav avoda zara askinan, it's
not related to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. It's a different concern. So
אמר רב חנינא מסורא, amar Rav Chanina misura, no, מה טעם קאמר.
mah ta'am ka'amar. The end is explaining the beginning. מה טעם אין
מברכין לא על הנר ולא על הבשמים של עכו"ם mah ta'am ein
mevarchin lo al haner velo al habesamim shel akum או של נכרי.
o shel nochri. Why can you not use a normal light or
fragrances of the non-Jews? מפני שסתם מסבת עובדי כוכבים לעבודה זרה mipnei
shestam mesibat ovdei kochavim l'avoda zara because we are concerned that it
came from things that were used at the feast and therefore it
would be connected to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Now in the end
though, that's how the גמרא Gemara does explain the בשמים besamim issue,
but נר ner remains the issue about the לא שבת lo shavat
as we are going to see. Hold on. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan.
אור ששבת מברכין עליו. or sheshavat mevarchin alav.
If the light rested, meaning it wasn't lit on שבת, Shabbos, you
make a ברכה bracha on it. ושלא שבת אין מברכין עליו. veshelo
shavat ein mevarchin alav. If not, if it was lit on שבת,
Shabbos, you cannot use it. מאי שבת ומאי לא שבת? mai shavat
umai lo shavat? What does it mean? Top of נ"ג עמוד א'.
nun gimmel amud aleph. So אי נימא לא שבת מחמת מלאכה. i
neima lo shavat machamat melacha. So if you say it means that
it did not rest from having done a מלאכה, melacha, so meaning
again presumably meaning it was not done in violation of שבת. Shabbos.
אפילו ממלאכה דהתירא, afilu mimelacha deheteira,
even if permissible? והתניא, vehatanya, אור של חיה ושל חולה מברכין עליו.
or shel chaya veshel choleh mevarchin alav.
If you lit a candle for a midwife or for somebody sick,
then you can use it. So that was done בהתירא. beheteira. So
as long as it was done בהתירא beheteira it's okay, even though
it was done on שבת. Shabbos. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק,
amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מאי שבת ששבת מחמת עבירה. mai shavat
sheshavat machamat aveira.
It doesn't mean it wasn't lit on שבת, Shabbos, it means it
wasn't lit in violation, which is a little bit funny because again
a non-Jew is not commanded. But somehow since it's not somehow licensed,
it's sort of conceptually it was lit on שבת Shabbos at the
sense of violation unless specifically it was lit with like under it
was with the it was a licensed type of a lighting which
was this case of פיקוח נפש. pikuach nefesh. So the point is
is that it was done on שבת Shabbos and it was seen
to violate שבת. Shabbos. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, with a
simile. עששית שהיתה דולקת והולכת כל היום כולו, ashashit shehayta doleket veholechet
kol hayom kulo, למוצאי שבת מברכין עליה. lemotza'ei Shabbos mevarchin aleha.
If you had some type of a lantern that was burning the
whole day, you could use it after שבת. Shabbos. So even that
also didn't rest, but the point was that was lit before שבת.
Shabbos. So it doesn't have to be that it wasn't burning on
שבת, Shabbos, but there's a sense that it didn't violate שבת. Shabbos.
Now there is debate, some have other גרסאות girsa'ot here that actually
you cannot use it and so on. But I will say since
יום כיפור's Yom Kippur coming up, a הלכה halacha that I have
to admit I never understood is that on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
so you don't have the idea of light as to remember that
במוצאי שבת אדם הראשון bemotza'ei Shabbos adam harishon created light. All it
is is to acknowledge that on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you cannot
light candles. And therefore from the הלכה halacha is you cannot make
fire. The הלכה halacha is on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you can't
use a new light. You have to use something that was lit
from before יום כיפור Yom Kippur and burning through יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. And that's called נר ששבת. ner sheshavat. I have to tell
you for my whole life I never understood that. If it's about
designating, demonstrating that you cannot light something, make fire on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, the best way to do it is to make a
new fire. All of a sudden because it says no, it has
to be נר ששבת, ner sheshavat, which means it was burning through
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. I don't know, maybe somehow that demonstrates that
the only way this was used was was Because it was lit
before, and therefore because we couldn't light it during, but again, I've
never really understood that. Here, clearly, the idea of נר ששבת, Ner
Sheshavat, although it includes being lit before, is fundamentally something that was
lit new afterwards.
Okay, so because it's almost, you know, it reminds me of the
Karaite thing. I mean, it's a ברכת הנהנין, birchos hanehenin, right?
No, not a ברכת הנהנין. birchos hanehenin. Then we were going to
get to that as a ברכת השבח. birchos hashevach. You don't make
the ברכה bracha and then נהנה. neheneh. You first sort of get
the הנאה hana'ah and then you make it. Rashi says people make
that mistake, but it's ברכת השבח. birchos hashevach. It's about you don't
make it during the rest of the week, right? It's only specifically
to be מכיר makir like again that, you know, that this is
the time where מכיר makir that
אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon created fire, God created fire, but it's essentially
ברכת השבח. birchos hashevach. But anyway, how is that related to your
Karaite thing that you?
Well, no, just like the idea of being able to use the
light on שבת... Shabbos...
use light on שבת. Shabbos. Oh, so maybe there's a particular point
of having something throughout שבת Shabbos to show against the Karaites about
it's against the לא תבערו בכל משבתיכם lo teva'aru bechol moshvoteichem that
it could be lit on שבת Shabbos and so on, and there's
a particular emphasis on that. But again, if that were true, then
why not require it on a normal מוצאי שבת? Motzei Shabbos? You
know, maybe, I don't know, anyway, but it is interesting this הלכה
halacha for יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Anyway, let's take a look. The
גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: נכרי שהדליק נר לישראל וישראל
שהדליק מנכרי, Nochri she-hidlik ner le-Yisrael ve-Yisrael she-hidlik mi-nochri,
if you lit your candle from the non-Jew or the non-Jew lit
it from you, מברכין עליו. mevarchin alav. Either way you can use
that for הבדלה. Havdalah. נכרי מנכרי אין מברכין עליו. Nochri mi-nochri ein
mevarchin alav.
However, if a non-Jew lit a candle from another non-Jew, you can't.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מאי שנא נכרי מנכרי דלא?
Mai shna nochri mi-nochri delo? Why a non-Jew from a non-Jew no?
משום דלא שבת, mishum delo shavat, because if it started with the
non-Jew, we assume it was lit on שבת Shabbos and it didn't
rest. So that's why you can't. אי הכי ישראל מנכרי נמי? Ei
hachi Yisrael mi-nochri nami?
So how about if the Jew lights from the non-Jew? It also
was comes from fire that did not that, you know, that did
not rest. So הלא שבת, halo shavat, it didn't rest. וכי תימא
הכי איסורא אזלה לה והכי אחרינא הוא וביד ישראל קמיתילדא, Ve-chi tema
hachi issura azla leh ve-hachi achrina hu u-beyad Yisrael kamisyalda,
and if you say okay, look, that which started with the non-Jew,
that was done with איסורא, issura, that's a light of violation, but
you took a light from that, you lit your candle from his
candle, so that's considered to be a different light. Okay, it's not
the same. So if that's true, אלא הא דתניא המוציא שלהבת לרשות
הרבים חייב, Ella hadetanya hamotzi shaleves lireshus harabbim chayav, now
the גמרא Gemara understands that not only because the ישראל Yisrael took
the light from the non-Jew, but also maybe we're saying that as
the fire continues to burn, it's always a new flame, right? What
is that famous, you know, what's that famous like there's there's this
Buddhist saying like you can't walk through the same river twice, and
then somebody says no, you can't walk through the same river once,
because
it's always, anyway, but okay, something like it's always changing. Anyway, so
if that's what you'll say that it's not the same, how about
what we talk in a ברייתא: Baraisa: המוציא שלהבת לרשות הרבים חייב?
hamotzi shaleves lireshus harabbim chayav?
If you take out a flame to רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, you're
חייב, chayav, and not because of the coal. The גמרא Gemara gives
an example that it's basically some type of an oil, you know,
on a shard, and it's burning, but there's not enough of the
shard to be חייב chayav for, the pottery shard, and you're חייב
chayav because you took out the flame. The flame is considered a
thing that you took out and you're חייב chayav for הוצאה. hotza'ah.
So it says אמאי חייב? Amai chayav? If you say it's always
changing, why are you חייב? chayav? מה שעקר לא הניח ומה שהניח
לא עקר. ma she-akar lo hiniach ve-ma she-hiniach lo akar. The flame
you picked up was not the flame you put down. אלא לעולם
דאיסורא נמי, Ella le'olam de-issura nami, so we say that the flame
remains.
וכי קממברך, Veki kamivarech, okay, so now fine, but then how again
can you bless it if a ישראל Yisrael took from a non-Jew?
We say אתוספת דהיתירא קממברך, Atosfes de-heteira kamivarech,
because part of it remains as ongoing, but then more is coming
that wasn't there. So when you're making the ברכה, bracha, it's on
the part that came after, the new stuff. Okay, so that could
be how it works if it came from a Jew came from
a non-Jew. So still then, a non-Jew from a non-Jew should be
okay. Even the non-Jew himself should be okay, because it continues to
burn after שבת Shabbos and the new stuff is okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי נכרי מנכרי נמי? Ei hachi nochri mi-nochri
nami? So a non-Jew from a non-Jew should also be okay. אין
הכי נמי גזירה משום נכרי ראשון ועמוד ראשון. Ein hachi nami gezeirah
mishum nochri rishon ve-amud rishon.
All of this is based on the concern that when it starts
with a non-Jew and it is the first flame. According to this,
the מסקנא maskana of the גמרא Gemara really seems to be, and
this is the way Rashi and Tosfos understand it where it's going,
is that technically even if it was lit on שבת, Shabbos, as
long as it was lit like a few minutes ago, an hour
ago, whatever, ten minutes, we don't know what it is, then we
consider what you have now is new fire mixed with old fire
and it would actually technically be good. So the whole thing is
not good because of the one case when it started with the
non-Jew and it is the flame that he, you know, that like
right after he lit it. He lit it five minutes before שבת
Shabbos was over. But really when a non-Jew takes from a non-Jew
it's fine, even the original non-Jew, it should be fine, even the
original non-Jew if you wait a little while it should be fine,
but because of that one case we אסרו assuru anything from the
original non-Jew and we אסרו assuru even a non-Jew from a non-Jew
because people won't make the distinction. And the only thing we allow.
And the only thing we allow is if in the end there's
some ישראל Yisroel involved. Sort of like becomes like almost the בישול
עכו״ם bishul akum stuff.
Anyway, whatever. So it becomes a little bit strange that we're all
worried about that one case. Yes.
So this נר של גויים ner shel goyim
is referring to the flame itself, right, not to say a candle
or a lamp that might have been used for עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah.
No, no, well we're not dealing with the עבודה זרה avodah zarah
concern right now, but no, like
if you
had a candle and you blew it out, right now we're talking
about the שבת Shabbos thing and then you relit the candle, that
would be fine. Yeah, so it's all about the flame. Okay, let's
now continue. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. היה מהלך חוץ לכרך. Haya mahalech
chutz lakrach. So now we're going to focus on בורא מאורי האש
borei meorei ha’eish by הבדלה. havdalah. You were going outside the city
וראה veraa
and you saw a fire. אם רוב נכרים אינו מברך, Im rov
nochrim eino mevarech, if most of the city is non-Jew, so you
can't make a ברכה, bracha, you have to assume it's from the
non-Jew. אם רוב ישראל מברך, Im rov Yisroel mevarech, if most were
for Jews, then you can. So the גמרא Gemara says הגופא קשיא,
Hagufa kashya, one minute, it's a contradiction. Why? אמרת אם רוב נכרים
אינו מברך, Amarta im rov nochrim eino mevarech, most non-Jews you can't,
הא מחצה על מחצה מברך, ha mechtza al mechtza mevarech, fifty-fifty you
can. והדר תני אם רוב ישראל מברך, Ve’hadar tani im rov Yisroel
mevarech, המחסא על המחסא אינו מברך. hamachtza al hamachtza eino mevarech. What
is it? Exactly fifty-fifty, you haven't said a good clear answer. So
בדיקנא B’dikna the גמרא Gemara says really דאפילו מחצה על מחצה נמי
מברך, de’afilu mechtza al mechtza nami mevarech, really you could do it
fifty-fifty as well. ואיידי דתנא רישא רוב נכרים תנא סיפא רוב ישראל.
Ve’ayedi detana reisha rov nochrim tana seifa rov Yisroel. Since we started
by saying majority non-Jews, we said in the end majority Jews, but
really fifty-fifty it's enough to rely on it for this ברכה. bracha.
All right, anyway the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. היה
מהלך חוץ לכרך וראה תינוק ואבוקה בידו. Haya mahalech chutz lakrach veraa
tinok va’avuka biyado. You saw an infant outside of the city with
a torch. בודק אחריו, Bodek achrav,
you inquire about it. אם ישראל הוא, Im Yisroel hu, if you
find out that this infant is a Jew, so מברך. mevarech. אם
נכרי הוא, Im nochri hu, if it's a non-Jew, אינו מברך. eino
mevarech. So that's pretty obvious based on what we've been saying. מאי
איריא תינוק, Mai irya tinok, why is it talking about a
תינוק, tinok, even an adult? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, הכא בסמוך לשקיעת החמה עסקינן. hacha besamuch lishkiat hachama
askinan. We're talking like right after sunset.
גדול Gadol must be like not sunset but also צאת, tzeit, it's
funny, he says שקיעת החמה. shkiat hachama. גדול מוכחא מילתא דבני נכרי
הוא. Gadol mocha milta devni nochri hu.
If it was an adult, then you know it's a non-Jew because
maybe he would not, you know, have lit a fire so close
to right after שבת. Shabbos. תינוק Tinok but if it's an infant,
אם ישראל הוא אקרי ונקיט, im Yisroel hu ikri venakit,
maybe it's a Jew and he just happened to grab a fire.
Again, I don't exactly get it because if the fire were lit
right before שבת Shabbos was over, then it's a problem, right, then
it's נר שלא שבת. ner shelo shavas. And if it was
possible that the child can make a fire so soon after שבת
Shabbos is over, why wouldn't an adult make the fire so soon
after שבת? Shabbos? So I really don't exactly get what the distinction
here is.
Or if the child is doing the
מלאכה melacha for the adult. Yeah, but then it should be the
problem about נר שלא שבת. ner shelo shavas. So, what? No, you
assume that
the child could not have lit the fire himself, right?
So he got it from an adult earlier.
Yeah,
while it was still שבת?
Shabbos? So that gets back to the point that it's נר שלא
שבת. ner shelo shavas. I don't get it. Okay, anyway, let's take
a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. היה מהלך חוץ לכרך וראה אור.
Haya mahalech chutz lakrach veraa or. You were outside the city and
you saw a fire. אם עבה כפי כבשן, Im ava kefi kivshan,
if it's as thick as like the fire in the mouth of
a kiln, so מברך עליו, mevarech alav, you make a ברכה. bracha.
ואם לאו אינו מברך עליו. Ve’im lav eino mevarech alav. What's that
about?
So now we're going to find out that you can only make
a ברכה bracha on a light that is lit for the purpose
of light, not that is lit for some other purpose, which again
is funny if the point of it is, either way you explain
it, either you're not allowed to, you know, make fire on שבת
Shabbos or the fire that אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon created, right, that's
more about fire than it is about light. But for whatever reason,
the ברכה bracha is מאורי האש. meorei ha’eish. It's about the light
of the fire, that's the part that you see, I guess. So
somehow we say you only make the ברכה bracha when it's lit
for the purpose of giving light, who made, what it is made
for the purpose of giving light. So if it
is very bright, so then you can, but if not you can't.
Why? So the גמרא Gemara says let's see how the גמרא Gemara
explains this. תני חדא אור של כבשן מברכין עליו, Tani chada or
shel kivshan mevorchin alav, you can by the fire of a kiln.
ותני אידך אין מברכין עליו, Ve’tani idach ein mevorchin alav, you can't.
לא קשיא. Lo kashya. הא בתחילה הא בסוף. Ha bitchila ha besof.
At the beginning, the whole purpose of the flame for the kiln
is to, you know, it's the purpose of making these, you know,
smelting the metal or whatever you're doing there. But at the end,
you want it to be bright because תוספות Tosafos says you want
to sort of you add flame to, you add like wood to
it or whatever you want it also to be bright so that
you can use it to do the type of work you do
after you've done the original smelt. So it's also for the purpose
of light. תני חדא אור של תנור ושל כירה מברכין עליו, Tani
chada or shel tanur veshel kira mevorchin alav, one ברייתא braisa says
if it's for an oven you can make a ברכה bracha on
it. ותני אידך אין מברכין עליו, Ve’tani idach ein mevorchin alav, you
can't. לא קשיא. Lo kashya. הא בתחילה הא בסוף. Ha bitchila ha
besof. Same type of a point, that somehow at the beginning it's
for the sake of cooking, at the end you also want it
or you add to it to make it for the sake of
light.
תני חדא אור של בית הכנסת ושל בית המדרש מברכין עליו. Tani
chada or shel beis haknesset veshel beis hamidrash mevorchin alav. If for
the use of the שול shul and for
the study hall you can make a ברכה. bracha. ותני אידך אין
מברכין עליו, Ve’tani idach ein mevorchin alav, one says you can't. לא
קשיא. Lo kashya. הא דאיכא אדם חשוב הא דליכא אדם חשוב. Ha
de’ika adam chashuv ha de’leika adam chashuv. When you are lighting candles
in a
שול shul or a בית מדרש... beis midrash... of the place and
it's not for the purpose of light. So it says if there's
a difference here is if there's an אדם חשוב. adam chashuv. So
רש״י Rashi says it means if there's an אדם חשוב adam chashuv
then you're doing it for his honor. תוספות Tosafos says no, the
opposite. Normally we assume in the בית כנסת beit knesset or the
בית מדרש beit midrash it's done for the honor of the holy
place. But if there's a חשוב chashuv person there maybe you want
to add a little extra so you're also doing it so that
he can see. So anyway in circumstances where it's also done for
the purpose of seeing there's a debate of the פוסקים poskim nowadays
I mean for us of course we know these lights are for
אור or and of course these count as light for בורא מאורי
האש borei meorei ha-eish separate discussion when actually when electric lights first
came out and the question was is it fire for שבת Shabbos
some rabbis were מקפיד makpid to use it for הבדלה Havdalah to
make the point that it was fire for שבת Shabbos but that
was anyway incandescent not fluorescent. Anyway but in the time of like
the פוסקים poskim where they had lights candles in the בית כנסת
beit knesset there was a question whether they were considered fundamentally there
for כבוד kovod or fundamentally there for light. Okay the גמרא Gemara
assumes by default we assume it's there for כבוד. kovod. ואיבעית אימא
ve-ibeit eima if you want you can say הא והא דאיכא אדם
חשוב ha ve-ha de-ika adam chashuv there is a חשוב chashuv person
there but it's still not clear whether it's for כבוד kovod or
for light. ולא קשיא הא דאיכא חזנא הא דליכא חזנא. ve-lo kashya:
ha de-ika chazana ha de-leika chazana. Is there a חזן chazan who
basically sleeps there and would need the light or not? So if
there's a חזן chazan we assume it's for light otherwise no. ואיבעית
אימא הא והא דאיכא חזנא. ve-ibeit eima: ha ve-ha de-ika chazana.
חזן Chazan here means more of a sexton than it means a
like a שמש shamash like a גבאי gabbai than it means like
the חזן. chazan. Anyway ולא קשיא הא דאיכא סהרא הא דליכא סהרא.
ve-lo kashya: ha de-ika sahra ha de-leika sahra. Is there a moon
out tonight? If there's a moon out then clearly it's there just
for כבוד. kovod. If there's not a moon it's there for light.
Okay. תנו רבנן היושבים בבית המדרש והביאו אור
לפניהם. tanu rabbanan: ha-yoshvim be-beit ha-midrash ve-heviu or lifnehem. You're sitting in
the בית מדרש beit midrash and they brought a fire and it's
מוצאי שבת. motzaei Shabbos. בית שמאי אומרים כל אחד ואחד מברך לעצמו.
Beit Shammai omrim: kol echad ve-echad mevarekh le-atzmo. Everybody should make the
ברכה beracha for himself. ובית הלל אומרים אחד מברך לכולם ve-Beit Hillel
omrim: echad mevarekh le-kulam משום שנאמר ברוב עם הדרת מלך. mishum she-ne'emar:
be-rov am hadrat melekh.
It's better to do it with everybody together. בשלמא בית הלל מפרשי
טעמא. bishlama: Beit Hillel mofarshei ta'ama. We understand the reason of בית
הלל. Beit Hillel. אלא בית שמאי מאי טעמא? ella Beit Shammai: mai
ta'ama? Why according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai should everybody make it
for himself? קסברי משום ביטול בית המדרש kasabri: mishum bittul beit ha-midrash
because I don't want them to stop learning. If you have to
get everybody together you have to get everybody quiet pay attention at
the same time. If I make it on my own time it
takes two seconds. Right
exactly! Exactly if I do it on my own schedule it takes
two seconds if we have to get everybody together it wastes more
time. Okay. תניא נמי הכי של בית רבן גמליאל לא היו אומרים
מרפא בבית המדרש. tanya nami hakhi: shel beit Rabban Gamliel lo hayu
omrim marpei be-beit ha-midrash. In the house of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
they didn't say gesundheit in a בית מדרש beit midrash מפני ביטול
בית המדרש mipnei bittul beit ha-midrash because of ביטול בית מדרש. bittul
beit midrash. So again a little bit
we're not good at this.
Well I have to tell you when people sneeze during the שיעור
shiur I'm usually not saying gesundheit but okay.
But yes this is the only source where this question comes up
with other things too like קידוש Kiddush and
הבדלה Havdalah about whether it's better to do ברוב עם be-rov am
or whether it's so that is a discussion
and we'll see actually a little bit of that is coming up
about whether it's גדול העונה יותר מן המברך gadol ha-oneh yoter min
ha-mevarekh or גדול המברך gadol ha-mevarekh and so on. So a little
bit of that is coming up there are other sources that relate
to that. Yes but some that is somewhat of the debate. Is
it בדיעבד be-di'avad to be יוצא yotzei through שומע כעונה shome'a ke-oneh
but what about the issue of ברוב עם be-rov am and that
actually does get the general assumption is as we know that ברוב
עם be-rov am is the better one. But yes some of that
does come up here it does not mention that it's a problem
of שומע כעונה shome'a ke-oneh here the only issue that comes up
is ביטול בית המדרש. bittul beit ha-midrash.
Okay now the גמרא Gemara continues אין מברכין לא על הנר ולא
על הבשמים של מתים. ein mevarchin lo al ha-ner ve-lo al ha-besomim
shel meisim. You can't use them if they were used for the
for the dead you know for way of like we'll see what
it was used what it's used. מאי טעמא נר לכבוד הוא דעבידא?
mai ta'ama: ner li-khvod hu de-avida? If they would bring out a
candle let's say in a funeral procession or put it by the
grave it was a way of showing honor it wasn't there for
light. ובשמים לעבורי ריחא הוא דעבידא u-vesomim: le-avori reicho hu de-avida and
the בשמים besomim the same way the fire has to be there
for light the בשמים besomim has to be there to provide for
the sake of providing positive aroma not just for cloaking bad. I
mean it's funny you use the positive aroma to cloak the bad
but somehow that was seen as not for the sake of ריחא.
reicho. It was fundamentally for the sake not for the sake to
give people a good smell you want to be smelling it but
it was there to cloak the bad smell. So because that's how
it was used for the מת meis it cannot be used for
בשמים. besomim. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב כל שמוציאין לפניו ביום ובלילה. amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav: kol she-motzi'in lefanav be-yom u-va-layla. If it's type of of
a corpse of a מת meis that you would take out candles
for it even if the procession was in the day obviously and
also night אין מברכין עליהן. ein mevarchin aleihen. Then you know the
candles are for כבוד kovod and you do not make it. וכל
שאין מוציאין לפניו אלא בלילה. ve-khol she-ein motzi'in lefanav ella ba-layla. If
it's type of מת meis you would only take out candles at
night for then it's not for כבוד kovod then it's for light
מברכין עליהן mevarchin aleihen and you can make the ברכה beracha on
it even though by the way you can't be נהנה neheneh from
a מת meis this is not considered to be connected enough to
the מת meis to extend that problem. אמר רב הונא בשמים של
בית הכסא amar Rav Huna: besomim shel beit ha-kissei if you bring
in fragrances into the bathroom to cloak the bad smell right or
like you know for us with those the little things that they
hang up, those air freshener things, okay? ושמן העשוי להעביר את הזוהמא,
u'shemen ha'asui lehaavir es hazuhama, or oil that you put on your
hands to get rid of the filth on your hands after a
meal, אין מברכין עליו. ein mevorachin alav. You don't make a ברכה
bracha on it because again, that is not for the sake of
providing good smell, it's for the sake of getting rid of bad
smell. Rashi is a little bothered because there's a גמרא Gemara before,
you remember, about making a ברכה bracha on שמן ערב. shemen areiv.
So anyway,
so תוספות Tosafot and רש''י Rashi deal with that issue about different
circumstances. Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
This would apply to such spices even if they're not in the
bathroom. Right, exactly.
Because of what purpose they serve. You know, or like an air
freshener, if you have air fresheners in your house, you know, assuming
that it would be a type of thing you would make a
ברכה bracha on otherwise, if it's fundamentally there because to cloak bad
smells you do not. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
where are we?
להעביר את הזוהמא אין מברכין עליו. lehaavir es hazuhama ein mevorachin alav.
למימרא דכל היכא דלאו לריחא עבידא לא מברכינן עליה. Lemeimra dechol heicha
delav lereicha avida la mevorachinan alei. Anytime it's not there fundamentally for
the sake of smelling,
you don't make a ברכה. bracha. מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on
this. We say, הנכנס לחנותו של בשם, hanichnas lechanuso shel bosem,
if somebody goes into the store of somebody selling perfumes and fragrances,
וריח ריח, ve'reiach reiach, and smells, אפילו ישב שם כל היום כולו,
afilu yashav sham kol hayom kulo, even if you're sitting the whole
day, אינו מברך אלא פעם אחת, eino mevarech ela paam achas, you
only make the ברכה bracha once. נכנס ויצא נכנס ויצא, nichnas ve'yatza
nichnas ve'yatza, if you're going in and out, מברך על כל פעם
ופעם, mevarech al kol paam vafaam, every time. The question is like,
how do you define different acts of smelling? By the way, I
should say parenthetically there's an interesting debate of the פוסקים, Poskim, is
it even if you smell inadvertently or only if you intend to
smell? Part of that goes back, if you remember, to the discussion
we had when we learned about the ברכה bracha of ריח, reiach,
whether it's like a ברכת הנהנין birchas hanenein or more of a
type of a more of a ברכת השבח. birchas hashevach. I mean,
so if it's a, you know, if it's a ברכת הנהנין birchas
hanenein and אסור להנות מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה, assur l'hanos min
ha'olam hazeh belo bracha, even if you're not intending to smell, in
the end you got the הנאה, hana'ah, you benefited from it and
so on, it might require a ברכה. bracha. So there's an interesting
debate of what if you're not intending. Anyway, there you have it,
making ברכות brachos when you go into this place. והכא דלאו לריחא
הוא דעביד וקא מברך. Vehacha delav lereicha hu de'avid veka mevarech.
There, it's not made for ריח reiach and you're making a ברכה.
bracha. I don't begin to understand that. What do you mean it's
not made for ריח? reiach? It's a perfumer! Presumably what the גמרא
Gemara means is he's not interested in you smelling the smells that
are in the store, he fundamentally, you know, wants you to buy
the product and go home, and the smells in the store here
are not there for people to be smelling. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says: אין לריחא נמי הוא דעביד, in lereicha nami hu de'avid,
it is made for smelling, היכי דנרחי אינשי וניתו וניזבנו מיניה. heicha
denirchi inshi venisvei venizbenu minei.
He wants people to smell so that they should come and buy
it. It's good advertising! Again, I don't even know what the הוה
אמינא hava amina was. Fundamentally even if it was inadvertent, it's not
like it was for some other purpose. It's just some smell escaped,
but the purpose of these fragrances is for being smelled, yes.
So when I go to the spice store to buy spices...
Yeah, you go to the McCormick spice factory, right? Or whatever, right.
Well, that's actually an interesting issue.
Do you make a ברכה bracha or not? Yeah, so that's the
question, do you make a ברכה bracha on הנאת ריח hana'as reiach
when it is not intended? Now, most of the time if you're
going there you'll say, oh that smells so good! Right? So that
in itself solves the problem. Then you're trying to smell.
And I should, I should probably say it before I go in?
Yeah, I mean, if you do it enough like immediately before you
step in. Yeah, I mean, I would say, you know, again, if
you, it takes some times maybe the smell doesn't hit you right
away. So I would wait till you begin to go in and
you're starting to smell, then make the ברכה bracha and then intentionally
smell. But there are some debates about that. Okay. So let's... yes?
So if this was ברכת הנהנין birchas hanenein or ברכת השבח?
birchas hashevach? Right, the ברכת הריח? birchas hareiach? Yeah, so that was
a little bit debated in the earlier גמרא. Gemara. It seemed to
be the debate. It seems like we side on the ברכת הנהנין
birchas hanenein because you make the ברכה bracha before you smell.
And you don't, you don't make it on every smell, right? If
you're baking bread, that smells good...
Right, that's true too. That's true, that's true. Right, right, that's true.
Although, it might be we should be making it a lot more
frequently than we do make it. But yeah. But that might have
to do with how you define לריחא עבידא, lereicha avida, that it's,
you know, not just smell but something that's there for the sake
of smell. But anyway, we do emphasize more the הנהנין hanenein and
you make it before you smell. Let's take a look, the גמרא
Gemara continues. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan:
היה
מהלך חוץ לכרך, haya mehalech chutz lakrach, you're going outside the city,
והריח ריח, ve'heriach reiach, so again, you don't know where the smell
is coming from. אם רוב עובדי כוכבים אינו מברך אם רוב ישראל
מברך, im rov ovdei kochavim eino mevarech im rov Yisrael mevarech, same
like before, you go by the majority, Jews or non-Jews. רבי יוסי
אומר אפילו רוב ישראל נמי אינו מברך. Rabbi Yosi omer afilu rov
Yisrael nami eino mevarech. Even most Jews you shouldn't make a ברכה.
bracha. Why? מפני שבנות ישראל מקטרות לכשפים. mipnei shebenos Yisrael mekatros lichshafim.
Sometimes these smells are made from Jewish women who are using it
for witchcraft. For, okay, burning incense for witchcraft purposes. אטו כולהו לכשפים
מקטרן? atu kulhu lichshafim mekatran? Do maybe most, why are we worried
about that?
No, הני דאיכא מיעוטא לכשפים, hani de'ika miuta lichshafim, no, here's the
answer, because there's a small number that does it for witchcraft or
whatever, ומיעוטא נמי לגמורי את הכלים. umiuta nami legamurei es hakelim. And
some use it for putting, you know, for sort of putting scent
into clothing. And interestingly that's also not considered לריחא. lereicha. לריחא lereicha
means very much for you to smell it directly. But if it's
done as a way of putting a scent into clothing, then that's
not considered לריחא. lereicha. So sometimes there's two of those possibilities exist
in terms of why this is even if it's coming from Jews.
השתא דרובא דלאו לריחא עבדי ליה hashta deruva delav lereicha avdei leh
I still don't know how that means that the majority winds up
to be not לריחא, lereicha, but anyway, that enough tips the scales
that you shouldn't make the ברכה bracha unless you know for sure.
I guess, I have no idea. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וכל רובא דלאו לריחא עבידא לא מברכינן. vechol ruba delav lereicha
avida lo mevorchinan. As long as
the majority is not that way, you don't make it. אמר רבי
חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן המהלך בערבי שבתות בטבריה Amar Rabi
Chiya bar Abba amar Rabi Yochanan hamehalech be'erevei shabbatot beTeveria ובמוצאי שבת
בציפורי. uvmotzaei shabbat beTzippori. If you're going ערב שבת erev shabbat in
Teveria or מוצאי שבת motzaei shabbat in Tzippori והריח ריח veherich reiach
and you smelled some nice fragrance, אינו מברך. eino mevarech. Don't make
a ברכה. bracha. מפני שחזקתו אינו עשוי אלא לגמר בו את הכלים
mipnei shechazkato eino asui ela legamer bo et hakeilim
because in those places, normally what they would do is in Teveria
ערב שבת, erev shabbat, they would burn incense or whatever fragrances in
order over clothing in order to get this nice smell into the
fabric. And in Tzippori they would do it מוצאי שבת. motzaei shabbat.
So therefore, that is for the sake of putting it in fabric
and you don't make the ברכה. bracha. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. היה
מהלך בשוק של עכו"ם hayah mehalech beshuk shel akum נתרצה להריח nitretzeh
leharich הרי זה חוטא. harei zeh chotei. And here again the question,
how do you define an act of smelling? You're going through such
a marketplace, and presumably here there is an עבודה זרה avodah zarah
concern, not just non-Jewish spices, and you want to, then you're sinning.
So to want to, it's interesting. There's a whole discussion in פסחים
Pesachim about this issue, about you have two paths to go on,
are you intending, not intending, it's a whole fascinating discussion of smell
as a type of a thing that can happen inadvertently, for how
halachically do we define an act of smelling. So here you see
the idea of נתרצה nitretzeh is a factor for the איסור, issur,
yes.
So this might be an issue when I go into the Indian
spice store.
One spice store is run by
Hindus, another's run by...
alright, I'm not getting into this. Let's read, I know it's late,
let's try to read at least, let's try to push till the
end, people have to go, fine, listen beyond the web. Anyway, ואין
מברכין על הנר עד שיאותו, ve'ein mevarchin al haner ad sheyeiotu, so
you don't make a ברכה bracha on the light until you get
benefit. Now here's important הלכה halacha that everybody assumes, oh, it's just
me and you Charlie. Maybe we should end here actually because it
feels a little funny. All right.